A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Rockefeller University Press, Journals, Correspondence and Financial Reports FA923
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Rockefeller University Press, Journals, Correspondence and Financial Reports
1914-1955
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University Press
FA923
1.32 Cubic Feet 3 boxes.
3 boxes.
History of journals published
Journal of experimental medicine: v. 1 (1896) and later numbers, Edited 1896-1904 by William Welch; 1905 and later under the auspices of the Rockefeller University; Supplement no. 1 (1921) and later numbers RG 543
Journal of general physiology v. 1 (1918) and later numbers, Edited by Jacques Loeb and W.J.V. Osterhout
Journal of biological chemistry v.1 (1905) and later numbers, Founded by Christian A. Herter, Published by the American Society of Biological Chemists; between 1914-1925 for the Journal of Biological Chemistry, Inc. by the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Journal of clinical investigation v. 1 (1924) and later volumes, Published by the American Society for Clinical Investigation and since July 1967 for the Society by the Rockefeller University Press
Journal of cell biology v. 1 (1955) and later volumes, Title varies: v. 1-11 (1955-1961), Journal of biochemical and biophysical cytology
Journal of lipid research v. 1 (1959/1960) and later volumes, Since v. 5 (1964) published by the Rockefeller University Press
Biophysical journal v. 1 (September 1960) and later numbers, Vol. 1 had 8 issues covering September 1960-November 1961, Published for the Biophysical Society
Special Volumes published in relation to the Journals:
The Journal of Experimental Medicine: 1921 vol. 34, no. 6 (Supple, 1) Louise Pearce. Trypanosmiasis; 1928 vol. 48, no. 2 (Supple. 2) Hideyo Noguchi. Trachoma III; 1930 vol. 52, no. 6 (Supple. 3) Florence Sabin, Charles A. Doan and Claude E. Forkner. Tuberculosis; 1971 vol. 134, no. 3, pt. 2 Immune Complexes (N.Y. Heart Association)
Cumulative Indexes: vols. 1-20 Author and subject (1896-1914); vols. 21-40 Author and subject (1915-1924); vols. 41-60 Author and subject (1925-1934)
The Journal of General Physiology: 1925-1928 vol. 8, nos. 1-6 Jacques Loeb Volume (NOT a supplement); 1960 vol. 43, no. 5, pt. 2 Physiology of Cell Membrane (IVIC); 1960 vol. 43, no. 6, pt. 2 Vision Mechanisms (IVIC); 1962 vol. 45, no. 4, pt. 2 In Honor of John Northrop; 1965 vol. 48, no. 5, pt. 2 Giant Axon of Squid (Proceedings); 1965 vol. 49, no. 1, pt. 2 Oxygen (N.Y. Heart Association); 1966 vol. 49, no. 6, pt. 2 Macromolecular Metabolism (N.Y. Heart Association); 1967 vol. 50, no. 6, pt. 2 Contractile Process (N.Y. Heart Association); 1968 vol. 51, no. 5, pt. 2 Cell Membrane Biophysics (IVIC); 1968 vol. 52, no. 1, pt. 2 Biological interfaces (N.Y. Heart Association); 1969 vol. 54, no. 1, pt. 2 Membrane Proteins (N.Y. Heart Association); 1970 vol. 56, no. 1, pt. 2 Interferon (N.Y. Heart Association)
Biophysics Journal: 1956 vol. 2, no. 2, pt. 2 International Biophysics Congress (Symposium); 1964 vol. 4, no. 1, pt. 2 Connective Tissue (Symposium)
Journal of Cell Biology (formerly Journal of Biophysical and Biochemical Cytology): 1956 vol. 2, no. 4, pt. 2 Tissue Fine Structure (Proceedings); 1961 vol. 10, no. 4, pt. 2 Veratti Supplement; 1965 vol. 25, no. 1, pt. 2 Flemming Supplement; (1965 vol. 25, no. 2, pt. 2 Backlog of regular articles); (1965 vol. 25, no. 3, pt. 2 Backlog of regular articles)
Cumulative author indexes vols. 1-11 (1955-1961) vol. 14, no. 2, pt. 2, vols. 12-31 (1962-1966) vol. 33, no. 1, pt. 2
Abstracts of Society meetings 1967 vol. 35, no. 2, pt. 2, 1968 vol. 39, no. 2, pt. 2, 1969 vol. 43, no. 2, pt. 2, 1970 vol. 47, no. 2, pt. 2
Note: In storage at the University are complete sets of all journal publications, unbound, including the supplements listed.
Biographical/Historical note
In order to assist in the dissemination of scientific investigations conducted at the Institute and elsewhere, publication was an early and important activity of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. A senior member of the scientific staff was usually the editor of a periodical. As early as 1910 the Institute had a Publication Service, which was supervised from 1910 by Editha C. Campbell until she retired in the fall of 1940. A Department of Illustration and Photography was under a part-time arrangement with De. Eduard Learning from 1906 until 1910 when Louis Schmidt undertook the direction of a full-time department. Louis Schmidt was at the head of the department until he reached the age of 70 in 1936. The work in the Department of Illustrations included hand-drawn illustrations for publications, photographs, moving pictures of experimental procedures made for the various investigators and used for a variety of purposes. Louis Schmidt served on a consultant basis until his death in 1939. Joseph Blauvelt Haulenbeek was acting in charge of Illustrations during that time and named officially in charge of illustrations in 1942, serving until he resigned September 1, 1946. Julian Alexander Carlile who was in charge of illustrations in the Department of Animal and Plant Pathology at Princeton took charge of the New York Department starting October 1, 1947 and divided his time between the two departments until they were consolidated during 1950. He directed the expanding department until his death in 1959 when he was succeeded by Richard F. Carter until 1964. In the academic year 1968/1969 Lewis William Koster became Manager of Graphic Services until 1973. March 1973 Bill Leyrer was appointed to that position.
Florence M. Stewart succeeded Editha Campbell in charge of the Publication Service in 1940 and served until she retired June 30, 1963, when she was succeeded by Margaret E. Broadbent.
Effective January 1, 1957 Charles Irvin Campbell was appointed Administrative Associate for Information Services. He had responsibility for a variety of information services among which were Secretary of the Library Committee, Librarian, ex officio, and supervision of the Publication Service and Illustration and Duplicating Services. Included were publication duties of such items as the Annual Report, Rockefeller Institute Quarterly, and the Calendar of Events. On October 20, 1958 the Board of Trustees approved a cooperative arrangement with the Oxford University Press to assist in producing, advertising and selling publications of the newly established Rockefeller Institute Press. The plan was for the Institute to continue publishing journals in accord with previously established policy and arrangements. Charles I. Campbell was appointed Director of The Rockefeller Institute Press. The Publications Service became the Journals Department without change of personnel or function. A new Books and Reports Department was created with responsibility for the production of books and the publication of bulletins and reports issued by the Institute.
January 1, 1960 Reynard F. Biemiller was appointed Assistant Director of The Rockefeller Institute Press. Effective December 5, 1960 Raymond B. Griffiths was appointed to the newly created position of Executive Editor of the Journal of Cell Biology.
Charles I. Campbell resigned May 15, 1962 and Joseph G. Sutton served as Acting Director of the Press from January 1963 until in 1964 William Arthur Bayless was named Director of the Press.
William Bayless retired as Director of The Rockefeller University Press on February 8, 1980. As of February 11, 1980, Mrs. Helene Jordan agreed to serve as acting director of the Press.
Effective July 1, 1980, Mrs. Helene Jordan was appointed Director of The Rockefeller University Press.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 517
Scope and Contents
Correspondence and reports.
Biology -- Research; Medicine, Preventive; Medical sciences; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Life sciences; Medical technology; Science -- Study and teaching; Medical research; Medical education
- Journal of General Physiology, 1918-1955; 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence and financial reports.
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is arranged in chronological order.
  - Financial reports, 1918-1947; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1938 1939-1957; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Including an outline of the editorial history of the Journal written March 7, 1955 by W.J.V. Osterhout. Correspondence is arranged in chronological order and deals primarily with number of pages per issue and covering letters sending manuscripts to the editors. Only in rare instances are editorial comments regarding scientific papers found. Most of the letters from W.J.V. Osterhout are handwritten.
  - Material dealing with v. 8 which was called Jacques Loeb Memorial Volume, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Forms and examples used for manuscripts (Box 1)
  - Advertisements in Science, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Material dealing with campaign to increase number of subscribers and special rates covering back volumes in sets and costs of reprinting certain volumes, 1 folder (Box 2)
- Journal of biological chemistry
  - Correspondence, 1914-1925 (Box 3)
    Including agreement for publication by RIMR for the Society and final decision to dissolve agreement.
    Correspondents include: A.H. Richards; H.D. Dakin; E.K. Dunham.
    Arranged in chronological order.
  - Report to the Directors and Financial Reports, 1915 (Box 3)
- Journal of clinical investigation
  - Correspondence, 1921-1950 (Box 3)
    Including copy of Rufus Col suggestion to Board of Scientific Directors for a new journal dealing with clinical investigations.
    Correspondents include: G.C. Robinson; James Harold Austin; Alfred E. Cohn. Correspondence is primarily about publication through RIMR and the decreasing subsidy from, the Institute.
- Journal of experimental medicine
  - Correspondence between Publications Division, Waverly Press and Charles Lindbergh concerning two publications, 1935-1943 (Box 3)
  - JEM 62 (1935) pp. 409-431: "An apparatus for the culture of whole organs" (Box 3)
  - JEM 70 (1939) pp. 231-238: "A culture flask for the circulation of a large quantity of fluid medium" (Box 3)
    Includes reprint, page proofs, illustrations, 2 signed typescripts from Charles Lindbergh and holograph from Peyton Rous.
  - "Charles Lindbergh developed first workable artificial heart pump" written by Webb Garrison and including a picture of Lindbergh with Alexis Carrel (Box 3)
    Photocopy of news item added 1977 October 11 from National Enquirer Latana, Fla.
  - Instructions about wording or statements to make or avoid when reporting on the use of animals in experiments, 1929-1952 (Box 3)
    Includes notes, memos and authorizations regarding some statements made in the journal. The exchanges are frequently with Peyton Rous as editor of the Journal.
  - Agreement with the MacMillan Co., Publishers, 1905 January 10; Carbon copy (Box 3)
- Journal of biophysical and biochemical cytology (Box 3)
  Announcement of start of publication.